"Benefits of Cumin and
Saffron for Weight Loss"
In my video, "Benefits of Black Cumin for
Weight Loss," a total of 17 randomized
controlled trials showed that
the simple spice could reduce
cholesterol and triglycerides.
And the side effects?
A weight-loss effect.
Saffron is another spice found
to be effective for treating
a major cause of suffering--
depression in this case--
with a side effect
of decreased appetite.
When put to the test in a randomized,
double-blind, placebo-controlled trial,
saffron, indeed, was found to
lead to a significant weight loss:
five pounds more than placebo,
and an extra inch off
the waist in eight weeks.
The dose of saffron used in
the study was the equivalent
of drinking a cup of tea made from
a large pinch of saffron threads.
Suspecting the active ingredient
might be crocin,
the pigment in saffron that
accounts for its crimson color,
researchers also tried giving people
just the purified pigment.
That led to weight loss, too,
but it didn't do as well
as the full saffron extract,
beating the placebo by only
two pounds and half an inch.
The mechanism appeared
to be appetite suppression,
as the crocin group ended up averaging
about 80 fewer calories a day,
whereas the full saffron group consumed
170 calories less a day on average.
A similar study looked specifically
at snacking frequency.
The researchers thought perhaps
the mood-boosting effects of saffron
might cut down on stress-related eating.
Indeed, eight weeks of a saffron extract
did cut snack intake in half, compared
to placebo, accompanied by
a slight but statistically significant
weight loss, about two pounds.
Even the loss of a few pounds is pretty
remarkable given the tiny doses utilized,
about 100 mg, which is equivalent
to about an eighth of
a teaspoon of the spice.
The problem is that saffron is the
most expensive spice in the world.
It's composed of delicate
threads sticking up out of
the saffron crocus flower.
Each flower produces only a few
threads, so you'd need 50,000 flowers
to make a single pound of spice--
enough flowers to cover a football field.
So that pinch of saffron
could cost a dollar a day.
That's why in my 21 tweaks to accelerate
weight loss in "How Not to Diet,"
instead of saffron,
I include black cumin,
which at a quarter teaspoon a day
would only cost three cents a day.
But what about just regular cumin?
Used in cuisines around the world
from Tex-Mex to South Asian,
cumin is the second most popular
spice on Earth after black pepper.
It's one of the oldest
cultivated plants with a range
of purported medicinal uses,
but only recently has it been
put to the test for weight loss.
Those randomized
to a half teaspoon
at both lunch and dinner
over three months
lost about four more pounds
and an extra inch off their waist.
The spice was found comparable
to the obesity drug known as orlistat.
For those of you who don't remember,
that's the "anal leakage" drug
you may have heard about, sold under
the brand names Alli and Xenical,
though the drug company
apparently prefers the term
"faecal spotting" to describe
the rectal discharge it causes.
The drug company's website
offered some helpful tips, though.
"It's probably a smart idea
to wear dark pants,
and bring a change of
clothes with you to work."
You know, just in case their drug
causes you to crap your pants at work.
I think I'll stick with the cumin,
thank you very much.